<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <dataset>
    <summary> GAIA DATA RELEASE 1 </summary>
    <remarks />
    <url>https://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/gaia/dr1</url>
    <icon>gaiadr1.png</icon>
    <docpage>gaiadr1.html</docpage>
  </dataset>
  <table name="[Source]">
    <remarks>It contains the basic source parameters, that is only final data (no epoch data) and no spectra (neither final nor epoch). </remarks>
    <column name="[solution_id]">
      <summary>
        Solution Identifier (long)
        The data in the MDB will be described by means of a ”Solution identifier” parameter. This will be a numeric field
        attached to each table row that can be used to unequivocally identify the version of all the subsystems that where
        used in the generation of the data as well as the input data used. Each DPC generating the data will have the freedom
        to choose the Solution identifier number, but they must ensure that given the Solution identifier they can provide
        detailed information about the ”conditions” used to generate the data: versions of the software, version of the
        data used…</summary>
      <quantity>meta.id</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[source_id]">
      <summary>
        Unique source identifier (long). A unique single numerical identifier of the source. For the contents of
        Gaia DR1, which does not include Solar System objects, the source ID consists consists of a 64-bit integer, least
        significant bit = 1 and most significant bit = 64, comprising:
        • a HEALPix index number (sky pixel) in bits 36 – 63; by definition the smallest HEALPix index number is zero.
        • a 2-bit Data Processing Centre code in bits 34 – 35; for example MOD(source_id / 4294967296, 8) can be used to
        distinguish between sources initialised via the Initial Gaia Source List by the Torino DPC (code = 0) and sources
        otherwise detected and assigned by Gaia observations (code &gt;0)
        • a 25-bit plus 7 bit sequence number within the HEALPix pixel in bits 1 – 32 split into:
        –  a 25 bit running number in bits 8 – 32; the running numbers are defined to be positive, i.e. never zero (except
        in the case of forced empty windows)
        –  a 7-bit component number in bits 1 – 7
        • one spare bit in bit 33
        This means that the HEALpix index level 12 of a given source is contained in the most significant bits. HEALpix
        index of 12 and lower levels can thus be retrieved as follows:
        • HEALpix level 12 = source_id / 34359738368
        • HEALpix level 11 = source_id / 137438953472
        • HEALpix level 10 = source_id / 549755813888
        • HEALpix level n = source_id / 2 ^ 35 * 4 ^ (12 – level).
        Additional details can be found in the Gaia DPAC public document Source Identifiers — Assignment and Usage throughout
        DPAC (document code GAIA–C3–TN–ARI–BAS–020) available from http://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/gaia/public-dpac-documents</summary>
      <quantity>meta.id;meta.main</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[random_index]">
      <summary>
        Random index used to select subsets (long)
        Random index which can be used to select smaller subsets of the data that are still representative. The column
        contains a random permutation of the numbers from 0 to N-1, where N is the number of rows.
        The random index can be useful for validation (testing on 10 different random subsets), visualization
        (displaying 1% of the data), and statistical exploration of the data, without the need to download all the data.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.dataset</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ref_epoch]">
      <summary>
        Reference epoch (double, Time[Julian Years]). Reference epoch to which the astrometic source parameters are
        referred, expressed as a Julian Year in TCB.</summary>
      <quantity>time.epoch</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra]">
      <summary>
        Right ascension (double, Angle[deg]) Barycentric right ascension α of the source in ICRS at the reference
        epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.ra;pos.frame=icrs</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra_error]">
      <summary>
        Standard error of right ascension (double, Angle[mas]). Standard error σα*≡σα⁢cosδ of the right
        ascension of the source in ICRS at the reference epoch ref_epoch.</summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;pos.eq.ra;pos.frame=icrs</quantity>
      <unit>mas</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec]">
      <summary>
        Declination (double, Angle[deg]). Barycentric declination δ of the source in ICRS at the reference epoch
        ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.dec;pos.frame=dec</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec_error]">
      <summary>
        Standard error of declination (double, Angle[mas]). Standard error σδ of the declination of the source
        in ICRS at the reference epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;pos.eq.dec;pos.frame=icrs</quantity>
      <unit>mas</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[cx]">
      <summary> Cartesian X (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.x;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[cy]">
      <summary> Cartesian Y (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.y;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[cz]">
      <summary> Cartesian Z (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.z;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[htmid]">
      <summary> HTM ID (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.HTM;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[zoneid]">
      <summary> Zone ID </summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.zone;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[parallax]">
      <summary>
        Parallax (double, Angle[mas] ). Absolute barycentric stellar parallax ϖ of the soure at the reference
        epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>pos.parallax</quantity>
      <unit>mas</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[parallax_error]">
      <summary>
        Standard error of parallax (double, Angle[mas] ). Standard error σϖ of the stellar parallax at the
        reference epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;pos.parallax</quantity>
      <unit>mas</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[pmra]">
      <summary>
        Proper motion in right ascension direction (double, Angular Velocity[mas/year] ). Proper motion in right
        ascension μα* of the source in ICRS at the reference epoch ref_epoch. This is the projection of the proper
        motion vector in the direction of increasing right ascension.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.pm;pos.eq.ra</quantity>
      <unit>mas yr-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[pmra_error]">
      <summary>
        Standard error of proper motion in right ascension direction (double, Angular Velocity[mas/year] ).
        Standard error σμα* of the proper motion vector in right ascension at the reference epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;pos.pm;pos.eq.ra</quantity>
      <unit>mas yr-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[pmdec]">
      <summary>
        Proper motion in declination direction (double, Angular Velocity[mas/year] ). Proper motion in
        declination μδ of the source at the reference epoch ref_epoch. This is the projection of the proper motion
        vector in the direction of increasing declination.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.pm;pos.eq.dec</quantity>
      <unit>mas yr-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[pmdec_error]">
      <summary>
        Standard error of proper motion in declination direction (double, Angular Velocity[mas/year] ).
        Standard error σμ⁢δ of the proper motion in declination at the reference epoch ref_epoch</summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;pos.pm;pos.eq.dec</quantity>
      <unit>mas yr-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra_dec_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between right ascension and declination (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between right ascension and declination, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra_parallax_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between right ascension and parallax (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between right ascension and parallax, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra_pmra_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between right ascension and proper motion in right ascension (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between right ascension and proper motion in right ascension, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra_pmdec_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between right ascension and proper motion in declination (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between right ascension and proper motion in declination, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec_parallax_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between declination and parallax (float, Dimensionless[see description]). Correlation
        between declination and parallax, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec_pmra_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between declination and proper motion in right ascension (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between declination and proper motion in right ascension, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec_pmdec_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between declination and proper motion in declination (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between declination and proper motion in declination, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[parallax_pmra_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between parallax and proper motion in right ascension (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between parallax and proper motion in right ascension, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[parallax_pmdec_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between parallax and proper motion in declination (float, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Correlation between parallax and proper motion in declination, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[pmra_pmdec_corr]">
      <summary>
        Correlation between proper motion in right ascension and proper motion in declination
        (float, Dimensionless[see description]). Correlation between proper motion in right ascension and
        proper motion in declination, in dimensionless units [-1:+1]</summary>
      <quantity>stat.correlation</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_obs_al]">
      <summary>
        Total number of observations AL (int). Total number of AL observations (= CCD transits) used in the
        astrometric solution of the source, independent of their weight. Note that some observations may be strongly
        downweighted (see astrometric_n_bad_obs_al).</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_obs_ac]">
      <summary>
        Total number of observations AC (int). Total number of AC observations (= CCD transits) used in the
        astrometric solution of the source, independent of their weight. Note that some observations may be strongly
        downweighted (see astrometric_n_bad_obs_ac). Nearly all sources having G &lt;13 will have AC observations
        from 2d windows, while fainter than that limit only ~1% of stars (the so–called ‘calibration faint stars’)
        are assigned 2d windows resulting in AC observations.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_good_obs_al]">
      <summary>
        Number of good observations AL (int). Number of AL observations (= CCD transits) that were not strongly
        downweighted in the astrometric solution of the source. Strongly downweighted observations (with downweighting
        factor w&lt;0.2) are instead counted in astrometric_n_bad_obs_al. The sum of astrometric_n_good_obs_al and
        astrometric_n_bad_obs_al equals astrometric_n_obs_al, the total number of AL observations used in the astrometric
        solution of the source.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_good_obs_ac]">
      <summary>
        Number of good observations AC (int). Number of AC observations (= CCD transits) that were not strongly
        downweighted in the astrometric solution of the source. Strongly downweighted observations (with downweighting
        factor w&lt;0.2) are instead counted in astrometric_n_bad_obs_ac. The sum of astrometric_n_good_obs_ac and
        astrometric_n_bad_obs_ac equals astrometric_n_obs_ac, the total number of AC observations used in the astrometric
        solution of the source.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_bad_obs_al]">
      <summary>
        Number of bad observations AL (int). Number of AL observations (= CCD transits) that were strongly
        downweighted in the astrometric solution of the source, and therefore contributed little to the determination
        of the astrometric parameters. An observation is considered to be strongly downweighted if its downweighting
        factor w&lt;0.2, which means that the absolute value of the astrometric residual exceeds 4.83 times the
        total uncertainty of the observation, calculated as the quadratic sum of the centroiding uncertainty, excess
        source noise, and excess attitude noise.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_n_bad_obs_ac]">
      <summary>
        Number of bad observations AC (int). Number of AC observations (= CCD transits) that were strongly
        downweighted in the astrometric solution of the source, and therefore contributed little to the determination
        of the astrometric parameters. An observation is considered to be strongly downweighted if its downweighting
        factor w&lt;0.2, which means that the absolute value of the astrometric residual exceeds 4.83 times the
        total uncertainty of the observation, calculated as the quadratic sum of the centroiding uncertainty, excess
        source noise, and excess attitude noise.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_delta_q]">
      <summary>
        : Hipparcos/Gaia proper motion difference (Hipparcos subset of TGAS only) (float). In the TGAS solution
        astrometric_delta_q (ΔQ) indicates the difference between the Hipparcos proper motion and the TGAS proper
        motion. A large value of ΔQ could indicate non-linear motion (e.g. in a binary).
        The precise definition is
        ΔQ=[Δ⁢μα*Δ⁢μδ]⁢(C→pm, T+C→pm, H)-1⁢[Δ⁢μα*Δ⁢μδ]
        where Δμα*=μα*,T-μα*,H, Δμδ=μδ,T-μδ,H, with T and H indicating values from the Gaia
        DR1 (TGAS) solution and Hipparcos catalogue. C→pm, T and C→pm, H are the corresponding 2×2
        covariance matrices.
        In order to compute ΔQΔ the two sets of proper motions must use the same reference frame and the same reference
        epoch. Thus, the proper motion components as given in the Hipparcos catalogue were rotated to the Gaia DR1
        reference frame, and then propagated to the Gaia reference epoch.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.pm;arith.diff</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_excess_noise]">
      <summary>
        Excess noise of the source (double, Angle[mas]). This is the excess noise ϵi of the source. It
        measures the disagreement, expressed as an angle, between the observations of a source and the best-fitting
        standard astrometric model (using five astrometric parameters). The assumed observational noise in each
        observation is quadratically increased by ϵi in order to statistically match the residuals in the
        astrometric solution. A value of 0 signifies that the source is astrometrically well-behaved, i.e. that
        the residuals of the fit statistically agree with the assumed observational noise. A positive value
        signifies that the residuals are statistically larger than expected.
        The significance of ϵi is given by astrometric_excess_noise_sig (DD). If D≤2 then ϵi is probably not
        significant, and the source may be astrometrically well-behaved even if ϵi is large.
        The excess noise ϵi may absorb all kinds of modelling errors that are not accounted for by the observational
        noise (image centroiding error) or the excess attitude noise. Such modelling errors include LSF and PSF
        calibration errors, geometric instrument calibration errors, and part of the high-frequency attitude noise.
        These modelling errors are particularly important in the early data releases, but should decrease as the
        astrometric modelling of the instrument and attitude improves over the years.
        Additionally, sources that deviate from the standard five-parameter astrometric model (e.g. unresolved binaries,
        exoplanet systems, etc.) may have positive ϵi. Given the many other possible contributions to the excess
        noise, the user must study the empirical distributions of ϵi and DD to make sensible cutoffs before
        filtering out sources for their particular application.
        In Gaia DR1, the excess source noise has the same interpretation as described above for both the primary (TGAS)
        and secondary data sets. It measures the disagreement between the five-parameter model and the observations,
        augmented by the different priors used. Thus, in TGAS the excess noise may be increased if the proper motion
        seen during the 14 months of Gaia observations are not in agreement with the proper motion inferred from the
        Tycho-2/Gaia comparison. In the secondary solution the excess noise may be increased if the Gaia observations
        indicate a proper motion or parallax several times larger than the prior uncertainty.
        The excess source noise is further explained in Sects. 3.6 and 5.1.2 of (1).</summary>
      <quantity></quantity>
      <unit>mas</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_excess_noise_sig]">
      <summary>
        Significance of excess noise (double). A dimensionless measure (DD) of the significance of the
        calculated astrometric_excess_noise (ϵi). A value D&gt;2indicates that the given ϵi is probably significant.
        For good fits in the limit of a large number of observations, DD should be zero in half of the cases and
        approximately follow the positive half of a normal distribution with zero mean and unit standard
        deviation for the other half. Consequently, DD is expected to be greater than 2 for only a few percent of the
        sources with well-behaved astrometric solutions.
        In the early data releases ϵi will however include instrument and attitude modelling errors that are
        statistically significant and could result in large values of ϵi and DD. The user must study the empirical
        distributions of these statistics and make sensible cutoffs before filtering out sources for their particular
        application.
        The excess noise significance is further explained in Sect. 5.1.2 of (1).</summary>
      <quantity></quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_primary_flag]">
      <summary>
        Primary or seconday (boolean). Flag indicating if this source was used as a primary source (true) or
        secondary source (false). Only primary sources contribute to the estimation of attitude, calibration,
        and global parameters. The estimation of source parameters is otherwise done in exactly the same way for
        primary and secondary sources.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.code</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_relegation_factor]">
      <summary>
        Relegation factor (float). Relegation factor of the source calculated as per Eq. (118) in (1) used
        for the primary selection process.</summary>
      <quantity></quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_weight_al]">
      <summary>
        Mean astrometric weight of the source (float, Angle[mas−2]). Mean astrometric weight of the
        source in the AL direction.
        The mean astrometric weight of the source is calculated as per Eq. (119) in (1).</summary>
      <quantity>stat.weight;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>mas-2</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_weight_ac]">
      <summary>
        Mean astrometric weight of the source (float, Angle[mas−2]). Mean astrometric weight of the
        source in the AC direction.
        The mean astrometric weight of the source is calculated as per Eq. (119) in (1).</summary>
      <quantity>stat.weight;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>mas-2</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[astrometric_priors_used]">
      <summary>
        Type of prior used in the astrometric solution (int).
        Type of prior used in the astrometric solution:
        • 0: No prior used
        • 1: Galaxy Bayesian Prior for parallax and proper motion
        • 2: Galaxy Bayesian Prior for parallax and proper motion relaxed by factor 10
        • 3: Hipparcos prior for position
        • 4: Hipparcos prior for position and proper motion
        • 5: Tycho2 prior for position
        • 6: Quasar prior for proper motion
        The Galaxy Bayesian Prior is defined in (2), where it is denoted σϖ,F90σϖ,F⁢90 (for the parallax) and
        σμ,F90=Rσϖ,F90 with R=10 yr−1-1 (for proper motion). The Galaxy Bayesian Prior relaxed
        by a factor 10 is 10σϖ,F90 and 10σμ,F90, respectively.
        For Gaia DR1 the only types of priors used are 2 (for the secondary data set), 3 (for the Hipparcos subset
        of the primary data set), or 5 (for the non-Hipparcos subset of the primary data set). Type 6 was used
        for internal calibration purposes and alignment of the reference frame, but the corresponding astrometric
        results are in general not published.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.code</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[matched_observations]">
      <summary>
        Amount of observations matched to this source (short). This field indicates the number of observations
        (detection transits) that have been matched to a given source during the last internal crossmatch revision.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[duplicated_source]">
      <summary>
        Source with duplicate sources (boolean). During data processing, this source happened to been
        duplicated and one source only has been kept. This may indicate observational, cross-matching or processing
        problems, or stellar multiplicity, and probable astrometric or photometric problems in all cases. In DR1,
        for close doubles with separations below some 2 arcsec, truncated windows have not been processed, neither
        in astrometry and photometry. The transmitted window is centred on the brighter part of the acquired window,
        so the brighter component has a better chance to be selected, even when processing the fainter transit. If more
        than two images are contained in a window, the result of the image parameter determination is un-predictable
        in the sense that it might refer to either (or neither) image, and no consistency is assured.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.code</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_strength_k1]">
      <summary>
        Degree of concentration of scan directions across the source (float). The scanDirectionStrength and
        scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions across the source. scanDirectionStrength[k−1]
        (k=1,2,3,4) is the absolute value of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θ is the
        position angle of the scan and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the
        astrometric parameters of the source. θ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is moving
        towards local North, and θ=90° towards local East.
        The scanDirectionStrength is a number between 0 and 1, where 0 means that the scan directions are well spread out
        in different directions, while 1 means that they are concentrated in a single direction (given by scanAngleMean).
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example, at first order
        (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second order (k=2) they are the
        same. Thus, scanDirectionStrength[0] is the degree of concentration when the sense of direction is taken into
        account, while scanDirectionStrength[1] is the degree of concentration without regard to the sense of direction.
        A large value of scanDirectionStrength[3] indicates that the scans are concentrated in two nearly orthogonal
        directions.</summary>
      <quantity>obs.param</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_strength_k2]">
      <summary>
        Degree of concentration of scan directions across the source (float). The scanDirectionStrength and
        scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions across the source. scanDirectionStrength[k−1]
        (k=1,2,3,4) is the absolute value of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θθ is the
        position angle of the scan and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the
        astrometric parameters of the source. θ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0θ=0 when the FoV is
        moving towards local North, and θ=90° towards local East.
        The scanDirectionStrength is a number between 0 and 1, where 0 means that the scan directions are well spread out
        in different directions, while 1 means that they are concentrated in a single direction (given by scanAngleMean).
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example, at first order
        (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second order (k=2) they are the
        same. Thus, scanDirectionStrength[0] is the degree of concentration when the sense of direction is taken into
        account, while scanDirectionStrength[1] is the degree of concentration without regard to the sense of direction.
        A large value of scanDirectionStrength[3] indicates that the scans are concentrated in two nearly orthogonal
        directions.</summary>
      <quantity>obs.param</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_strength_k3]">
      <summary>
        Degree of concentration of scan directions across the source (float). The scanDirectionStrength
        and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions across the source.
        scanDirectionStrength[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is the absolute value of the trigonometric moments
        mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θθ is the position angle of the scan and the mean value is taken over
        the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric parameters of the source. θ is defined in
        the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is moving towards local North, and θ=90° towards
        local East.
        he scanDirectionStrength is a number between 0 and 1, where 0 means that the scan directions are well
        spread out in different directions, while 1 means that they are concentrated in a single direction
        (given by scanAngleMean).
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example, at
        first order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second order
        (k=2) they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionStrength[0] is the degree of concentration when the
        sense of direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionStrength[1] is the degree of concentration
        without regard to the sense of direction. A large value of scanDirectionStrength[3] indicates that the
        scans are concentrated in two nearly orthogonal directions.</summary>
      <quantity>obs.param</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_strength_k4]">
      <summary>
        Degree of concentration of scan directions across the source (float). The scanDirectionStrength
        and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions across the source.
        scanDirectionStrength[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is the absolute value of the trigonometric moments
        mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θ is the position angle of the scan and the mean value is taken over
        the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric parameters of the source. θ is defined
        in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is moving towards local North, and θ=90°
        towards local East.
        The scanDirectionStrength is a number between 0 and 1, where 0 means that the scan directions are well
        spread out in different directions, while 1 means that they are concentrated in a single direction
        (given by scanAngleMean).
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example, at first
        order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second order (k=2)
        they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionStrength[0] is the degree of concentration when the sense of
        direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionStrength[1] is the degree of concentration without
        regard to the sense of direction. A large value of scanDirectionStrength[3] indicates that the scans are
        concentrated in two nearly orthogonal directions.</summary>
      <quantity>obs.param</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_mean_k1]">
      <summary>
        Mean position angle of scan directions across the source (float, Angle[deg]). The
        scanDirectionStrength and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions
        across the source. scanDirectionMean[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is 1/k times the argument
        of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θθ is the position angle of the
        scan and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric
        parameters of the source. θθ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is
        moving towards local North, and θ=90° towards local East.
        scanDirectionMean[k-1] is an angle between −180°/k and +180°/k, giving the mean
        position angle of the scans at order k.
        The different orders kk are statistics of the scan directions modulo 3605°/k. For example,
        at first order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second
        order (k=2) they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionMean[0] is the mean direction when the sense
        of direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionMean[1] is the mean direction without
        regard to the sense of the direction. For example, scanDirectionMean[0] = 0 means that the scans
        preferentially go towards North, while scanDirectionMean[1] = 0 means that they preferentially
        go in the North-South direction, and scanDirectionMean[4] = 0 that they preferentially go either
        in the North-South or in the East-West direction.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.posAng;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_mean_k2]">
      <summary>
        Mean position angle of scan directions across the source (float, Angle[deg]). The
        scanDirectionStrength and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions
        across the source. scanDirectionMean[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is 1/k times the argument
        of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θθ is the position angle of the
        scan and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric
        parameters of the source. θθ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is
        moving towards local North, and θ=90° towards local East.
        scanDirectionMean[k-1] is an angle between 180°/k and +180°/k, giving the mean
        position angle of the scans at order k.
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example,
        at first order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second
        order (k=2) they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionMean[0] is the mean direction when the sense
        of direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionMean[1] is the mean direction without regard
        to the sense of the direction. For example, scanDirectionMean[0] = 0 means that the scans
        preferentially go towards North, while scanDirectionMean[1] = 0 means that they preferentially go
        in the North-South direction, and scanDirectionMean[4] = 0 that they preferentially go either in
        the North-South or in the East-West direction.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.posAng;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_mean_k3]">
      <summary>
        Mean position angle of scan directions across the source (float, Angle[deg]). The
        scanDirectionStrength and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions
        across the source. scanDirectionMean[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is 1/k times the argument
        of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θ is the position angle of the
        scan and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric
        parameters of the source. θ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0 when the FoV is
        moving towards local North, and θ=90° towards local East.
        scanDirectionMean[k-1] is an angle between -180°/k and +180°/k, giving the mean
        position angle of the scans at order k.
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example,
        at first order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at second
        order (k=2) they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionMean[0] is the mean direction when the sense
        of direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionMean[1] is the mean direction without regard
        to the sense of the direction. For example, scanDirectionMean[0] = 0 means that the scans
        preferentially go towards North, while scanDirectionMean[1] = 0 means that they preferentially go
        in the North-South direction, and scanDirectionMean[4] = 0 that they preferentially go either in
        the North-South or in the East-West direction.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.posAng;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[scan_direction_mean_k4]">
      <summary>
        Mean position angle of scan directions across the source (float, Angle[deg]). The
        scanDirectionStrength and scanDirectionMean quantify the distribution of AL scan directions
        across the source. scanDirectionMean[k-1] (k=1,2,3,4) is 1/k times the argument
        of the trigonometric moments mk=⟨exp(i⁢k⁢θ)⟩, where θθ is the position angle of the scan
        and the mean value is taken over the nObs[0] AL observations contributing to the astrometric
        parameters of the source. θθ is defined in the usual astronomical sense: θ=0θ=0 when the FoV is
        moving towards local North, and θ=90∘θ=90∘ towards local East.
        scanDirectionMean[k-1] is an angle between -180°/k and +180°/k, giving the mean
        position angle of the scans at order k.
        The different orders k are statistics of the scan directions modulo 360°/k. For example,
        at first order (k=1), θ=10° and θ=190° count as different directions, but at
        second order (k=2) they are the same. Thus, scanDirectionMean[0] is the mean direction when
        the sense of direction is taken into account, while scanDirectionMean[1] is the mean direction
        without regard to the sense of the direction. For example, scanDirectionMean[0] = 0 means that
        the scans preferentially go towards North, while scanDirectionMean[1] = 0 means that they
        preferentially go in the North-South direction, and scanDirectionMean[4] = 0 that they
        preferentially go either in the North-South or in the East-West direction.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.posAng;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[phot_g_n_obs]">
      <summary>
        Number of observations contributing to G photometry (int). Number of observations (CCD transits)
        that contributed to the G mean flux and mean flux error.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.number</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[phot_g_mean_flux]">
      <summary>G-band mean flux (double, Flux[e-/s]). Mean flux in the G-band. </summary>
      <quantity>phot.flux;em.opt.G</quantity>
      <unit>ct s-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[phot_g_mean_flux_error]">
      <summary> Error on G-band mean flux (double, Flux[e-/s]). Error on the mean flux in the G-band. </summary>
      <quantity>stat.error;phot.flux;em.opt.G</quantity>
      <unit>ct s-1</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[phot_g_mean_mag]">
      <summary>
        G-band mean magnitude (double, Magnitude[mag]). Mean magnitude in the G band. This is computed
        from the G-band mean flux applying the magnitude zero-point in the Vega scale.</summary>
      <quantity>phot.mag;meta.number;stat.mean</quantity>
      <unit>mag</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="phot_variable_flag">
      <summary>
        Photometric variability flag (string, Dimensionless[see description]).
        Flag indicating if variability was identified in the photometric G band:
        ”NOT_AVAILABLE” = source not processed and/or exported to catalogue
        ”CONSTANT” = Source not identified as variable
        ”VARIABLE” = source identified and processed as variable, see tables:
        phot_variable_summary,
        phot_variable_time_series_gfov,
        phot_variable_time_series_gfov_statistical_parameters,
        and cepheid or rrlyrae for more details.
        Note that for this data release only a small subset of (variable) sources was processed and/or exported,
        so for many (known) variable sources this flag is set to ”NOT AVAILABLE”. No ”CONSTANT” sources were
        exported either.</summary>
      <quantity>meta.note</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[l]">
      <summary>
        Galactic longitude (double, Angle[deg]). Galactic Longitude of the object at reference
        epoch ref_epoch, see ESA, 1997, ’The Hipparcos and Tycho Catalogues’, ESA SP-1200, Volume 1,
        Section 1.5.3, for the conversion details.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.galactic.lon</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[b]">
      <summary>
        Galactic latitude (double, Angle[deg]). Galactic Latitude of the object at reference epoch
        ref_epoch, see ESA, 1997, ’The Hipparcos and Tycho Catalogues’, ESA SP-1200, Volume 1, Section
        1.5.3, for the conversion details.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.galactic.lat</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[ecl_lon]">
      <summary>
        Ecliptic longitude (double, Angle[deg]). Ecliptic Longitude of the object at reference epoch
        ref_epoch, see ESA, 1997, ’The Hipparcos and Tycho Catalogues’, ESA SP-1200, Volume 1, Section 1.5.3,
        for the conversion details.</summary>
      <quantity>pos.ecliptic.lon</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[ecl_lat]">
      <summary>
        Ecliptic latitude (double, Angle[deg]). Ecliptic Latitude of the object at reference epoch
        ref_epoch, see ESA, 1997, ’The Hipparcos and Tycho Catalogues’, ESA SP-1200, Volume 1, Section 1.5.3,
        for the conversion details.</summary>
      <quantity>ecliptic.lat</quantity>
      <unit>deg</unit>
    </column>
  </table>
</metadata>