<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
  <dataset>
    <summary>  Dark Energy Survey </summary>
    <remarks>
      The Dark Energy Survey (DES) is a five-year program (2012B-0001, PI Josh Frieman) using the Dark Energy Camera (DECam)
      on the CTIO Blanco 4m telescope to image 5,000 square degrees of sky in 5 bands (g, r, i, z and Y), and to carry out a
      time-domain survey of repeated visits over 30 square degrees. The primary goal of DES is to probe the origin of
      accelerating cosmic expansion through measurements of galaxy clusters, weak lensing, galaxy clustering, and type Ia
      supernovae. However, the data are valuable for many other astronomical applications.
      The DES-Y1 data release consists of science observations taken between September 2013 and early February 2014,
      covering roughly 1800 square degrees of the survey footprint in the South Galactic Cap. This includes more than
      160 sq. degrees overlapping the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) Stripe 82 region, and about 20 visits to ten of
      the DES supernova fields. This release includes 13,890 DECam exposures that have been reduced and calibrated
      through the DES Data Management (DESDM) pipeline at the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA).</remarks>
    <url>http://www.darkenergysurvey.org/</url>
    <icon>des.png</icon>
    <docpage>des.html</docpage>
  </dataset>
  <table name="[dbo].[PhotoObj]">
    <remarks></remarks>
    <column name="[cx]">
      <summary> Cartesian X (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.x;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[cy]">
      <summary> Cartesian Y (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.y;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[cz]">
      <summary> Cartesian Z (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.z;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[htmid]">
      <summary> HTM ID (J2000)</summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.HTM;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[zoneid]">
      <summary> Zone ID </summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.zone;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[seqID]">
      <summary> sequential ID </summary>
      <quantity>meta.record</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dtpropid]">
      <summary> NOAO proposal identification, or generic program identifier for data without assigned proposal ID. </summary>
      <quantity>meta.id</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[surveyid]">
      <summary> The survey ID. AS not all NOAO data re from surveys, this may be a blank value. </summary>
      <quantity>meta.id</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[release_date]">
      <summary> Date for public release of the data. </summary>
      <quantity>time.release</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[start_date]">
      <summary> Calendar data (not UT) at start of observing night. </summary>
      <quantity>time.start;obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[date_obs]">
      <summary> UT date and time, from DATE-OBS header keyword. Not available for all instruments. </summary>
      <quantity>time.epoch</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dtpi]">
      <summary> Principal investigator </summary>
      <quantity>meta.id.PI</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[ra]">
      <summary> Right ascension </summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.ra;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
      <unit> deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[dec]">
      <summary> Declination </summary>
      <quantity>pos.eq.ra;pos.frame=j2000</quantity>
      <unit> deg</unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[telescope]">
      <summary> Telescope </summary>
      <quantity>instr.tel</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[instrument]">
      <summary> Instrument </summary>
      <quantity>instr</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[filter]">
      <summary> Filter used for observation. Not available for all instruments. </summary>
      <quantity>instr.filter</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[exposure]">
      <summary> Exposure time. Not available for all instruments. </summary>
      <quantity>obs.exposure</quantity>
      <unit> s </unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[obstype]">
      <summary> Type of observation, from OBSTYPE header keyword. Not available for all instruments. </summary>
      <quantity>obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[obsmode]">
      <summary> A newer FITS keyword indicating the type of observation mode. Older files may sometimes lack any value for this. </summary>
      <quantity>obs</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[proctype]">
      <summary>
        Data processing type: Raw (raw data), INstCal(pipeline-calibrated single exposure), Resampled (calibrated image
        onto sky plane), Skysub (skysubstracted NEWFIRM image), Stack (coadded sum of a sequence of exposures), or MasterCal
        calibration file).</summary>
      <quantity>meta.dataset</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[prodtype]">
      <summary> Data product type: Image, Dqmask (data quality mask), Expmap (Exposure map for stacked images), png (preview image). </summary>
      <quantity>meta.dataset</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[seeing]">
      <summary> Average seeing FWHM in arcsec. AVailable for pipeline-processed imaging data only. </summary>
      <quantity>instr.obsty.seeing</quantity>
      <unit> arcsec </unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[depth]">
      <summary> Approximate 5-sigma photometric depth for piont sources. Available for pipeline-processed imaging data only. </summary>
      <quantity></quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[dtacqnam]">
      <summary> Original data file name supplied at the telescope by the observer or data-taking system. </summary>
      <quantity>meta.id;meta.file</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[archive_file]">
      <summary> Filename assigned to a data file in the NOAO Science Archive. All files are renamed to unique names when they enter the </summary>
      <quantity>meta.id;meta.file</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[filesize]">
      <summary> File size in bytes </summary>
      <quantity>phys.size;meta.file</quantity>
      <unit> byte </unit>
    </column>
    <column name="[reference]">
      <summary> reference to fits file. </summary>
      <quantity>meta.ref;meta.file</quantity>
    </column>
    <column name="[md5sum]">
      <summary> md5sum is used to verify that a file has not changed as a result of a faulty file transfer, a disk error or non-malicious </summary>
      <quantity>meta</quantity>
    </column>
  </table>
</metadata>